<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Dave Longman</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Dave Longman</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Dave Longman</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 17:07:19 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Moving beyond folders: Using Document Sets in SharePoint</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/moving-beyond-folders-part3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/moving-beyond-folders-part3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the thrid and final article in the SharePoint document management series. This series explains how you can make use of more advanced features to improve the way you store and manage documents in SharePoint. You can read the first article &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/blog/moving-beyond-folders-part1/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Why are folders a poor way to organise documents -&amp;gt; no cascade of properties, different properties to documents&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;What are Document Sets&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Shared properties&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Folders and templates within Document Sets&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving beyond folders: Keeping document metadata consistent in SharePoint</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/moving-beyond-folders-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/moving-beyond-folders-part2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the second of a three part series explaining how you can make use of more advanced features to improve the way you store and manage documents in SharePoint. You can read the first article &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/blog/moving-beyond-folders-part1/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;What is the problem with defining metadata within the library?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Site Content vs Tenant Content Types&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Search Rollup&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Challenge with multiple documents in a folder needing the same metadata -&amp;gt; fixed with Document Sets&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving beyond folders: Managing document metadata in SharePoint</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/moving-beyond-folders-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/moving-beyond-folders-part1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have recently completed some work for a local charity supporting their rollout of SharePoint to replace an old fileshare. This work reminded me how confusing SharePoint can be for new users, especially when it comes to using it to replace a traditional file server. Out of the box, SharePoint has some fantastic benefits over a fle share, such as automatic file versioning, soft deletion support with the multi-stage recycle bin and the ability to easily access and share documents without needed a VPN. But if you just continue to use SharePoint in the same way you did with a fileshare you are missing out on loads of additional capability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting the future: How much work is in our backlog?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/predicting-the-future-part4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/predicting-the-future-part4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the final instalment of our Predicting the Future series. In previous articles, we’ve discussed the basics of estimating and forecasting and covered some techniques to predict how long new work may take using historical data. In this article, I’m going to outline evidence-based forecasting, an approach that helps predict how much work is contained within an entire product backlog. (Warning: there is some maths involved once again, but it’s really just averages and counting.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting the future: How big is this project – and when will we complete it?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/predicting-the-future-part3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/predicting-the-future-part3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the third in our four-part series on estimating and forecasting. In this instalment, we’ll be looking at ways to forecast how long a project, feature, or group of stories might take using historical data and some simple mathematics. In the last article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/blog/predicting-the-future-part2/&#34;&gt;we used cycle time to forecast&lt;/a&gt; how long a single story is likely to take the team. While this is a useful exercise and can be helpful for product owners when they’re reviewing the backlog, the more common question is: “Will we be able to complete this group of stories by this date?”. Or, more specifically, something like: “Can we complete the payment gateway upgrade before the holiday season?”. And that’s what we’re to attempt to answer in this article.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting the future: how long will a story take?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/predicting-the-future-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/predicting-the-future-part2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Understanding how long a single story is likely to take is important when a team is planning work and valuable for product owners when they’re maintaining the product backlog and forming high-level release plans. But what’s the best approach to forming an estimate?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A lot of teams focus primarily on velocity when planning. They look at the average number of points they complete within an iteration and use this to indicate how many they’re likely to finish in the next one. This is a good approach if you need a quick estimate for how much work to include in an iteration, but it relies on all work having its own story point estimate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting the future: estimates, forecasts, and the value of knowing what’s coming next</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/predicting-the-future-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/predicting-the-future-part1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After 10 years of living in our house, my wife and I started thinking seriously about building an extension. Soon, we were immersed in the world of construction – a space neither of us are particularly knowledgeable about.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When you don’t know the industry – or what the work entails – you’re never sure if your ideas are workable, super-complicated, or totally out of your budget. Would an extension cost us £20k? Or £100k? We may like the look of local slate flagstones, but they’re £10k; is there an alternative that looks similar but costs, say, £2k instead?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Working from home and its impact on productivity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/wfh-productivity-impact/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/wfh-productivity-impact/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-world-of-work-has-changed&#34;&gt;The world of work has changed&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The impact of the Coronavirus pandemic has meant that millions of people have been forced to work from home – with many having to make this adjustment at very short notice.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Office for National Statistics says that 49% of UK workers reported working from home at some point in the seven days to 14 June 2020. The fact that so many people have now had this experience is likely to lead to a major change in working practices in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
